Priority and leadership eh I Center Party consider that many of
labor market issues in the first place should be handled by
had in Sweden a tradition of eh and that is because it is after all
Labor market policy works at I level or at home in Sweden should detail
The labor market, for example, through the works quotation or
The wage guarantee hike, on the other hand, should, after all, guarantee all people's
equal rights and opportunities for example by ensuring protection against
After all, discrimination and the Center Party have worked actively on the issue of EU
common standards for equality body
Eh what is then equivalent to discrimination as the man in Sweden we
have pushed on politically for the Council of Ministers to adopt
functional right and that is the anti -racist perspective and by having these three
different glasses all the time on in on it when we work with
Legislation so we believe that we can also take concrete steps forward in terms of increased
Diversity but one last thing I want to say is that representation Matters and
It doesn't matter how eh how well one speaks of diversity
If you look at the parties' lists, I think that including my own party
I am equally critical of all, so it leaves a part to be desired in terms of eh
diversity of different candidates so we have a lot to do and work on both
internally in political life at home in Sweden that party political life but
also
[Music] Legislative Power to Mikaela afterwards
lift up these issues eh at an eunal level for there is risk then we
Compromise with what works well in Sweden and we don't want to do that
I still emphasize eh so should see a little more jo eh yes but one thing like me too
want to say that is that a challenge ahead we think is that if one now as well as
proceed at eunal level to go into these issues and that it becomes for
Of course, detail rules eh there are a number of conventions that are eh that are
very good and I know abir mentioned this with working to
Disabled people should be given rights in working life and so on and that is
something that all of which all countries must take their responsibility and the EU states there
the strengthened in terms of basic human rights and that we must
protect eh all people so it is important but we don't think we need
lift it up at euns level with special directives in that way and then begins
Finally with regard to EH companies' sustainability reporting, we think that
It is very good thus this CS RD Directive EH which was one of the questions
from you but I still want to say that we may be careful so that it does not become
Too great workload for small businesses so that you can't cope with that
becomes too much administration It is clear that large companies can handle this
good but but we must also make sure not to have too much eh detail regulation in
In the EU that's what I wanted to say thank you so very big thanks Mikael thanks for
That then I think I should invite the next representative and then it will be Karin
representing the Liberals and I will say that I know that several of you are
after all in the middle of campaign several of these candidates eh so that it is very happy
That you are with us I know Karin is one of those who are on the move but
Please Karin thank you so much eh yes my name is
Karin Karlsbro I am the top candidate of the Liberals eh I'm just as you said
I'm on a trip I'm on my way to Stockholm but right now I'm sitting on
a park bench in beautiful Gränna so I Mikaela in your home areas and it was
Great to be able to share the morning coffee and a little lovely moment in this
hectic time with you and talk about these important issues and
Before I became a European Parliamentarian as I became in 2019, I worked as
sustainability manager in the real estate industry so that these issues are also lies
personally in the professional life very hot about
weaker EU or a decent EU and then we want to exactly
on the contrary, we think that the issue of human rights for that is
actually what we talk about democrat and human rights is a matter
that lacks boundaries that we have to handle jointly together over
national borders and between countries that they are far too important to not yes
simply ending a pact globally and we have at the UN level global level eh come
a bit late in compliance catastrophic but eunal level is actually very important for
these issues and at this time where we yes wrestle with war with freedom
and oppression and we see how democracy is mounted down in several EU countries and threatened
I think primarily about what has happened in Hungary development in Hungary de
In recent years, we should be aware that eh EU Europe is not vaccinated either
against eh one one very negative development and there the EU comes in and we
thinks it is important that just these issues of human rights
actually lies at euns level that's not details that is where this is exactly where we
eh then when it comes to eh sustainability reporting and the eh de
the questions then there is something that is left to stay and we also see in
other eula law that social sustainability is woven in I have to
Example negotiated EU's
Sustainability to do you can think of yes today when we work with such a pretty
Technical really climate law founding so you weave in human rights eh
working conditions eh elsewhere in the world so that it is also linked to
This but in the end the EU is one union and should be and we have to guard guard
about E's role as union for democracies and then racism eh homophobia has Islamophobia
In anti -Semitism and all that now we can put words into has no place in our
Union and then we together have to set up rules EH that counteracts eh hatred and
threats and the restriction of
AG and organizations jobs together in the same direction but don't forget EU weight in
Magnus Pevin and is Municipal Restsjö but also number four on the Environmental Party's list
to the euval and it is very exciting times eh right now of course
And I would have been out and campaigned today too but have I gone on throat flux
So I get to sit at home and take care of the work digitally instead of this term of office
That has passed has been extremely important and we have mainly had Alice here
Bakke as our eh pioneer so to speak in these work areas and she got
already at the beginning of the term of office as
main hearing on democracy and equality and anti -discrimination
which we are very proud of the work needs to be ongoing and it needs to be
powerful and we need to put a very strong pressure on the Commission EH
For this is about human rights, thus to be able to work to
able to have a job no matter who one is whether one has a disability
or not where one comes from or whatever it may be about is about
human rights and here we don't have to be so frightened around it
The Swedish model because this is about a framework legislation at EU level
that must antiden discrimination legislation to
Examples that have been blocked since 2008 thus for 16 years it is absolutely incredible
convinced that in fact, sometimes with legislation must be told
How you want and how we want it to look like the increased gaps de ekon omis
Increased gaps, not least in Sweden, perhaps increasing among the OECD countries
is a challenge as well for the labor market and here one cannot then
as the Swedish government go in and say that we remove the contribution to
employers who have high sick pay costs that are total
counterproductive, but we must increase the security of people at
the labor market to be able to be retrained to be able to become employed even if one has one
disease picture behind it that our companies should feel confident in hiring the right
competence even though this person seeking the work has previously been
Sick -sick, for example, then you cannot reduce the contributions to that way
eh in some kind of ideal world create incentives for more people to come in
work without we believe that it is totally counterproductive but basically as I said
So I have to say that this is about human rights and fearful
the hot around the Swedish model or speech that the EU should be v law on it
may not be about human rights these are frame laws that need to and
Then it is up to Sweden and the Labor Market Party to make sure that
It will be reality thank you very much thank you also to you Magnus Eh and then
I think I leave the word to Evin representing
be seen and must be included eh I have myself during this term of office
that has gone as sitting as, among other things, in a cross -political intergroup
and called eh anti anti -racism and diversity eh intergroup where i have
Worked, among other things, with these eh inclusion FRR
Ågor an eh important eh question as or an important legislation that has been raised
As I think is worth mentioning again as like the EU should EH continue to negotiate
around and then assume it is after all
I think that would be a hugely important step forward to it I must too
may also mention that I mean in the EU's eh fundamental rights statute so is
all of course the inclusion anti -racism and everything like that is very very or
Anti -discrimination very very clear so all of all EU's really
function variation eh so with that said there is very much to
do but one of the most important things comes in the coming term of term V
would actually be to ensure one
Big thanks also to you Evin for that then I think I give the word of course
Also to Jesper who represents the Moderates big eh big thank you too
for the opportunity to be with you here today eh yes but the EU should include a
collaboration that increases idea exchange between countries eh that also spreads good
Example reinforced exchange of experience is and and will remain
One of the foremost forms of cooperation in the labor market and the EU should, of course
Of course, put the majority of their power and focus on issues where intercourse
required eh war threat and the weak competitiveness for example we
Moderates yes but we believe that labor market policy should be designed by
Member States themselves eh it is our way of safeguarding the Swedish model it
also provides the opportunity to develop the same I think it is also worthwhile to
note when I listen to this discussion that companies that are more
Equal more inclusive also have higher profitability over time tips eh
At the same time, I would like to emphasize that the EU should ensure that all member states
have good protection against discrimination we moderates also think it is
Reasonable for the Statute of Rights to be extended with certain additional rights and here
Need the EU to ensure that every country takes responsibility for its part in that commitment
Eh you can describe it as the floor needs to be raised and the whole toolbox
Need to be used then there was a question in advance regarding the CSR directive eh
thanks big thanks Jesper eh and now I think I leave the word to z as
represents the Left Party please thank you very much and good morning
From a little goaln North Tälje ehm I I work within the Left Party
with education about anti -racism so it is very fun to be here and
get talk about eh yes but equality and discrimination with you
ehm today we have a rather insufficient insufficient picture of the width of
discrimination within the Union EH Although there are guidelines from the Commission
If equality data we still lack a common picture of perceived
discrimination when we work for quite a few different parameters
The Left Party EH thinks we need a clearer directive regarding
equality data based on voluntariness he he iT and
Especially self -identification eh A clearer directive would help countries
Like, for example, Sweden not to be so embarrassingly bad at bringing statistics
an allocated gender affiliation in the EH Census Register
The Left Party wants the Swedish model with Partfinder
trade union rights eh for others we want the EU to change procurement rules
eh so it becomes possible to make demands on collective agreements at all public
Procurement without exception eh in the third we want to
Labor immigration shall be based on the salary and conditions that apply in
Sweden or other EU countries should also apply to what immigrants we cannot
retain this system we have now leading to pay dump and bad
working conditions eh it only drives on segregation eh and creates great social
and economic differences that provide racist power structures ehm that it
structural racism is reflected in our workplaces is
No wonder as long as we pursue on increased segregation at the same time eh like that
We reduce this segregation, we want to see at least that labor market parties
where both employers receive greater responsibility and trade unions more tools for
put pressure on companies regarding equal eh action but then it is so that
We have an ever -growing gig and platform economy with extensive many
negatively racist workers who are completely out of backing from
trade unions ehm and if we don't get buck on it so
Will we not get very far that is why we want platform companies to
regarded as employer and platform work should be regarded as
workers to enable
party interrogation what everyone has mentioned a bit about the ehm eh left party is positive
to EH systems like CSR what enables companies to take responsibility for their entire
However, value chains eh we want the requirements for companies to be raised for
Environmental and Social Ehm Social Sustainability Ehm therefore we want
that justice should be a more central part of CSR and that legislation should in a lot
The Center Party first yes very wisely has been said and it is
Great fun to see that there is such a commitment to the question EH but I think
that somewhere if I am to stick to today's theme and that n I
organizes about precisely diversity in the labor market and how to think then eh
Work for it so there is very much thrown with concepts here as in eh
I do not want to be the one that is that shows that one really does not
Join this match we have then a labor market policy in Sweden that is
Swedish and according to the EU City City, it should be the case that labor market policy
It is a national matter and I think it is a good and good order
It has served us well now there are then some groups that have not been allowed to join
And where we then have in Sweden because of the Swedish labor market model but
Also on GR of the inability of the social parties to also have inclusion and
diversity in their negotiation rounds as a priority
Ask eh also ended up in the aftermath and created high thresholds for people who
Do not meet the requirements of the norm yes I just want to give an example so svia
would hire people to Arlanda and on that on the ad they had so had
they wrote that one of the requirements is that eh those who seek work work must be able to
fluent Swedish in speech and writing when they then got when they got a lot
Applications but no one really was good enough to be able to work there
And then they got help from some diversity expert and this diversity
The expert studied the workplace and studied the job ad and then realized
This this consulting company that really so you don't have to have eh
fluent and great Swedish in speech and writing to 90 % of the time as
The people who work for Swedavia talk about language other than just Swedish so
After all, we have an outdated an outdated way of working in recruitment what
applies to seeing people's skills we have after all
giant otter skills for example we we usually laugh a little but it is a
Incredibly great finds we make we have the world's most educated
Taxi driver training
Both have politics with them but also the social parties I am quite critical
where one does not have a conscious work on having members of their
organizations that have a different background and actually give them space one of my
Biggest Problem has been in politics has been that yes abir yes exactly it was
just like this is clear we all want to join and discuss thanks so much
And thanks for like concrete examples, I think it also helps to
Understand the Eun level so thank you so much I apologize for interrupting but I
Thinking everyone should catch up and comment on something and Mikaela I thought
I leave the word to you yes but thank you very much I think it was
very interesting and it is interesting what abir says about validation it is
The of course incredibly important it has been pushing for a long time that one must become a lot
much better at being able to do it eh eh and precisely in terms of
If she's on the run but I leave the word but i'm with yes well so hello yes no
But very very wise have said when I thought maybe a few questions in order to
You should get a clearer picture of the differences between the parties
Also and eh that I started with so the Liberals are a very European friend LT
party because we believe we need stronger cooperation on all the issues there
We have to solve common problems or where we need to guard the joint
Right is we are we are so positive about the EUSAM work so we want Sweden
shall change the crown with the euro for example eh but labor market policy is after all is
After all, it is national and we also guard the Swedish model but
At the same time, we are challenged by eh new business models new new
forms of employment, so to speak and then I think of gigg work and there have
strengthen women's eh labor market and gender equality in the labor market eh and
Then you usually get the question as a letter on the post what do you think about
Quotation to corporate boards it is a hot issue and here has the Liberals
landed in the fact that we are we think it is a bad idea with quotation to
Board of Directors without we have to find other seats but yes these issues
If you are often wrestled in when talking about this kind of eh of questions so
that yes I just wanted to clarify some points where we often get questions I
Stay there thanks great thanks Karin Eh for that eh
Magnus I thought the word is going to you now yes but thanks so much no but it is
many things that have been said here and that are important to lift up I believe and not
At least that CS RD Directive is completely deciding and where we are with our green
main hearing on precisely that one should be able to increase the requirements of reporting social
human rights and diversity issues but this needs
Go further this applies to companies with 500 employees and a turnover of 40
Million euro eh there are thus very few companies actually that end up here
And we believe that the companies that may be at the forefront that can report that they
are sustainable will also win in the future because we will set
requirements for public procurement, for example, we already have many companies that
themselves set demands in their procurement of subcontractors and need to get in
This type of reports then of course needs smaller companies one
Support in this accounting and it is quite obvious eh it is so that when
one talks about these things to happen at eunal level the parties that often talk about
Jesper we shall use the intergovernmental European cooperation to
Sweden should be able to be more freer safer and richer but there seems to be a picture
in many that it will become reality by the fact that the entire EU must become eh exactly
As Sweden and otherwise member states, in principle, EH should be sent out of the Union
And here I find it important to have the perspective that the EU can work
purposefully constructive and long -term to persuade member states that
really meet the minimum requirements for human rights it is through
This continuous work eh in processing these countries inside the Union
as we can make sure that Jews in Hungary Roma in Romania women in Poland get a
better or at least a decent eh life situation and it is difficult to
Write it on a Vala Fish like a slogan eh but this is this continuous
the work of raising the floor and using the toolbox within the Union it is as
We can get a working union to feel eh pride
because yes thank you so much Jesper and eh last but not least in this round so
I leave the word to the Zi Left Party please thank you very much eh and I want to
This important eupa -parliament election but big thanks for all
To all of you who took and so Anna you get closing words this thank you very much
Liselott and thank you very much all you who have also what is called signed in and
Participates in this one and wants to engage more in and use your voice
And above all, V of course thank all of you who are running for now I know you have
Extremely hectic time both behind you and in front of you so I am so happy that you have
Taken to time to be here and I am very happy Liselott that you took that time
to moderate this important conversation and diversity charter swen for us is after all
Like this foundation it is the human rights we like
After all, under the EU Commission and we are, as I said, we do not take any party but we
Still believe in collaborating so just like Lis said used